A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Natural Resources, 1992-2006 (bulk 2002-2005)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Natural Resources, 1992-2006 (bulk 2002-2005)
The Library of Virginia
42294, 42398, 42458
51 cu. ft. (137 boxes; one map case drawer).
Virginia Office of the Secretary of Natural Resources
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. When possible, privacy-protected information has been redacted. If redaction was not an option, the entire document was sealed, but not removed from the collection. Sealed or redacted information may include, but is not limited to: attorney-client privileged documents, medical information, social security numbers, proprietary information, confidential settlement documents, and court documents filed under seal. Sealed court documents can be viewed with proof that the seal has been lifted. Attorney-client privileged documents are closed indefinitely.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Carol B. Denson, Office of the Secretary of Natural Resources, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia 23219, 9 November 2005 (Accession 42294), 12 January 2006 (Accession 42398), 24 January 2006 (Accession 42458).
Biographical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governor's top management team. The Office of Secretary of Commerce and Resources was created on April 8, 1972. The Secretary of Commerce and Resources was responsible for assisting the Governor in implementing policies for the conservation and use of natural resources, for promoting economic development, providing managerial guidance and direction to Commerce and Resources agencies, and developing and promoting Commerce and Resources programs and budgets. In 1984 the Secretariat was split into two separate offices, the Secretary of Economic Development and the Secretary of Natural Resources.
The Secretary of Natural Resources is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, and is subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. During the administration of Governor Mark R. Warner, the Secretary of Natural Resources was responsible for the direction of, or had jurisdiction over, the following state agencies and boards: Chesapeake Bay Local Assistance Department (which became a division of the Department of Conservation and Recreation on July 1, 2004), Department of Conservation and Recreation, Department of Environmental Quality, Department of Game and Inland Fisheries, Department of Historic Resources, Marine Resources Commission, Museum of Natural History, Chippokes Plantation Farm Foundation, and the Virginia Council on Indians. The Secretary of Natural Resources also served as the chairman of the Virginia Land Conservation Foundation, and was a Board Member of the Chesapeake Bay Commission. Additionally, the Secretary of Natural Resources was responsible for many smaller boards and commissions related to water control, pollution, rivers, waste management, and other environmental and recreational issues.
On December 28, 2001, Governor-Elect Mark R. Warner announced his appointment of W. Tayloe Murphy, Jr. as Secretary of Natural Resources. Prior to this appointment, "Tayloe" Murphy represented the 99th House district (Northern Neck region) in the Virginia House of Delegates from 1982 to 2000. While a member of the General Assembly, Murphy served as Chairman of the Chesapeake Bay Commission, and was also chairman of the Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission during a two-year review of the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality. He served as co-chairman of the House Labor and Commerce committee and held a seat on the committee on Corporations, Insurance, and Banking. As a Delegate, he was instrumental in the passage of both the Chesapeake Bay Preservation Act and the Virginia Water Quality Improvement Act. Mr. Murphy served as Secretary of Natural Resources until the end of Governor Warner's term in January 2006.
On January 5, 2002, Governor-Elect Warner announced his appointment of David K. Paylor as Deputy Secretary of Natural Resources. Paylor had previously served as Director of Program Coordination for the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality (DEQ) from 1998 to 2002. He also served as DEQ's Regional Permits Director and Director of the Office of Spill Response and Remediation. From 1977 to 1992, Paylor worked in various roles at the Virginia Water Control Board, including Water Resources Manager. Paylor served as Deputy Secretary until the end of the Warner administration.
In November 2001, Governor-Elect Warner appointed Russell W. Baxter as Assistant Secretary for Chesapeake Bay Coordination. Previously, Baxter had served as the Virginia director and senior policy analyst for the Chesapeake Bay Commission. Baxter served as Assistant Secretary throughout Governor Warner's term in office.
Information about this office is also available in the archived website files of the Office of the Secretary of Natural Resources, (2005-2006). They can be found by searching the Library of Virginia's catalog using "Secretary of Natural Resources" as the subject.
Scope and Content
Constituent and internal correspondence, appointment records, legislative files, photographs, speeches and other working papers and records created and collected by the Office of the Secretary of Natural Resources during the gubernatorial term of Virginia Governor Mark R. Warner, 2002-2006. This collection consists of nine records series which document the activities of the Office of the Secretary of Natural Resources, as well as the agencies and boards which fall under its heading.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Agency and Board Appointment Records, 2001-2005
Series II. Appointment Calendars, 2002-2005
Series III. Correspondence and Supporting Documents, Agencies, 1992-2006
Series IV. Correspondence and Supporting Documents, Constituent, 2002-2006
Series V. Correspondence and Supporting Documents, Secretary W. Tayloe Murphy, 1997-2006
Series VI. Decision Briefs, 2001-2006
Series VII. Legislative Initiatives, 2002-2005
Series VIII. Public Relations Files, 2001-2005
Series IX. Special Program Files, 1999-2005
Contents List
- Series I. Agency and Board Appointment Records, 2001-2005., Extent: 1.2 cu. ft. (Box 1-4.)
  Contains memorandums, correspondence, nominations, and resume material for, from, and about citizens who were appointed to agency and board positions within the Natural Resources secretariat by Governor Mark R. Warner. Also included are board profiles which explain the purpose and goals of many of the boards and commissions overseen by the Secretary of Natural Resources. This series provides information about the appointment process, as well as background on those chosen to serve. Much of the material is devoted to the earliest appointments made by Governor Warner.
  Appointment files are arranged alphabetically by subject and then chronologically within. Board profiles maintain their original alphabetical arrangement under state agency headings. (Accession 42398).
  - Agency Appointment Records, 2002.
    - Agency appointments (general information), 2002. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Agency Head Resumes, 2002. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board Appointment Records, 2002-2003.
    - Board appointments (general information), 2002. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Board appointments (general information), 2002-2003. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Board appointments (general information), 2003. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Air Pollution Control Board, 2002-2005. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Alexandria Historical Restoration and Preservation Commission, 2002. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Breaks Interstate Parks Commission, 2004-2005. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cave Board, 2002-2005. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Chesapeake Bay Advisory Boards, 2002-2005. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Chesapeake Bay Local Assistance Board, 2002-2004. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Chickahominy State Scenic River Advisory Board, 2002. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Chippokes Plantation Farm Foundation, 2002-2005. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Board of, 2001-2003. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Board of, 2003. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Board of, 2003-2005. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Falls of the James Scenic River Advisory Board, 2002. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Game and Inland Fisheries, Board of, 2001-2003. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Game and Inland Fisheries, Board of, 2003-2005. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Historic Resources, Board of, 2002. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Historic Resources, Board of, 2002-2005. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Land Conservation Foundation, 2002-2005. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Litter Control and Recycling Fund Advisory Board, 2002-2005. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Local Government Advisory Committee, 2002. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Marine Resources Commission, 2002. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Marine Resources Commission, 2002-2003. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Marine Resources Commission, 2003-2004. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Marine Resources Commission, 2004. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Marine Resources Commission, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Mount Vernon, Board of Visitors to, 2003-2005. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Museum of Natural History, Board of Trustees, 2002-2004. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Museum of Natural History, Board of Trustees, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Potomac River Basin Commission (Interstate Commission on the Potomac River Basin), 2002-2005. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Potomac River Fisheries Commission, 2002. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Roanoke River Basin Advisory Committee, 2002. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Scenic Rivers Advisory Boards, 2002. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Scenic Rivers Advisory Boards, 2002-2005. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Soil and Water Conservation Board, 2002-2005. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - State Water Commission, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - State Water Control Board, 2002. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - State Water Control Board, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - State Water Control Board, 2003-2005. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Tennessee Valley Regional Resource Stewardship Council, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Coastal Land Management Advisory Board, 2003. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Land Conservation Foundation, Board of, 2002. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Natural Resources Foundation, Board of Trustees, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Virginia Outdoors Foundation, Board of Trustees, 2002-2005. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Virginia Recreational Facilities Authority, 2002-2005. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Recycling Markets Development Council, 2002. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Virginia State Parks Foundation, Board of Trustees, 2002. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Virginia Waste Management Board, 2002-2005. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Board Profiles, 2002-2003.
    - Board profiles (general information), 2002. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Chesapeake Bay Local Assistance Board, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of, (general information on boards under its heading) 2002. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Breaks Interstate Park Commission, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Cave Board, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Chippokes Plantation Farm Foundation, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Conservation and Development of Public Beaches, Board on, 2002. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Conservation and Recreation, Board of, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Invasive Species Council, 2003. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Lower James Historic River Advisory Committee, 2003. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Scenic River Advisory Boards, 2002. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Scenic River Advisory Boards, 2002. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Scenic River Board, 2003. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Virginia Land Conservation Foundation, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Virginia Outdoors Foundation, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Virginia Outdoors Foundation--Regional Open-Space Preservation Advisory Boards (Regions 1-6), 2002. (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Virginia Soil and Water Conservation Board, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of--Virginia State Parks Foundation, Board of Trustees, 2002. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Environmental Quality, Dept. of (general information on boards under its heading), 2002. (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Environmental Quality, Dept. of--Air Pollution Control Board, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Environmental Quality, Dept. of--Litter Control and Recycling Fund Advisory Board, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Environmental Quality, Dept. of--Small Business Environmental Compliance Advisory Board, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Environmental Quality, Dept. of--State Water Control Board, 2002-2003. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Environmental Quality, Dept. of--Virginia Recycling Markets Development Council, 2002-2003. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Environmental Quality, Dept. of--Virginia Waste Management Board, 2002-2003. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Game and Inland Fisheries, Dept. of--Game and Inland Fisheries, Board of, 2002-2003. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Historic Resources, Dept. of--Virginia Historic Preservation Foundation, Board of Trustees, 2002. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Historic Resources, Dept. of--Virginia Historic Resources Board, 2002-2003. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Marine Resources Commission, Virginia, 2002-2003. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Natural History, Virginia Museum of, Board of Trustees, 2002-2003. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series II. Appointment Calendars, 2002-2005., Extent: 2 folders. (Box 4.)
  Contains the monthly appointment calendars of Secretary of Natural Resources, W. Tayloe Murphy, Jr.
  Arranged chronologically by month. (Accession 42398).
  - Appointment calendars, 2002-2003. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Appointment calendars, 2004-2005. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series III. Correspondence and Supporting Documents, Agencies, 1992-2006., Extent: 19 cu. ft. (Box 5-58.)
  Contains correspondence, memorandums, reports, meeting material, and other working papers which document relations between the Office of the Secretary of Natural Resources and several of the agencies and boards under its heading including the Chesapeake Bay Local Assistance Department (CBLAD), Department of Conservation and Recreation (DCR), Virginia Council on Indians (VCI), Department of Environmental Quality (DEQ), Department of Game and Inland Fisheries (DGIF), Department of Historic Resources (DHR), Virginia Marine Resources Commission (MRC), and the Virginia Museum of Natural History (MNH). Also included are files pertaining to the Secretary's involvement as a board member of the Chesapeake Bay Commission (CBC). Many of the records in this series contain information on various natural resources-related projects and issues, while other files contain agency-specific administrative information, general correspondence (including a limited amount of constituent correspondence), agency strategic plans, and meeting material, including agendas, print-outs of presentations, and minutes.
  Arranged alphabetically by agency or board name, then alphabetically within. Files containing information on the Natural Resources secretariat as a whole can be found at the beginning of the contents list. (Accessions 42294 and 42398).
  - Agency General Information, 2002. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Agency General Information, 2002. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Agency General Information, 2002. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Agency General Information, 2002. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Agency General Information, 2003-2005. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Agency Head Meeting, 2005 August. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Agency Head Meeting, 2005 September. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Agency Strategic Plans, 2003. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Agency Strategic Plans--Chesapeake Bay Local Assistance Department, 2003. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Agency Strategic Plans--Conservation and Recreation, Department of, 2003. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Agency Strategic Plans--Conservation and Recreation, Department of, 2003. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Agency Strategic Plans--Environmental Quality, Department of, 2003. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Agency Strategic Plans--Game and Inland Fisheries, Department of, 2003. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Agency Strategic Plans--Historic Resources, Department of, 2003. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Agency Strategic Plans--Marine Resources Commission, 2003. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Agency Strategic Plans--Natural History, Virginia Museum of, 2003. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Chesapeake Bay Commission, 1994-2005. (Box 6-11.)
    The Chesapeake Bay Commission (CBC) is a tri-state, legislative assembly comprised of cabinet members, legislators, and citizen representatives of Virginia, Maryland, and Pennsylvania. The Commission was created in 1980 to coordinate Bay-related policy across state lines and to develop shared solutions. The Chesapeake Bay Commission focuses on a wide variety of issues affecting the health and well-being of the Chesapeake Bay.
    Contains an abundance of meeting material including agendas, minutes, hand-outs, and presentations collected by the Secretary of Natural Resources in his capacity as an active member of the Chesapeake Bay Commission. Also included is meeting material and information pertaining to Governor Mark Warner's involvement with the Chesapeake Executive Council. Additionally, this subseries contains information on the Chesapeake Bay Agreement 2000, and the work done by the Commission to protect the Bay, its tributaries, and its living resources.
    Researchers should be aware that additional records pertaining to the Secretary's involvement with the Chesapeake Bay Commission can be found under the heading of Conservation and Recreation, Department of. It is unknown why these records were filed in two places by the office staff, and as a result there may be some overlap.
    - Bi-State Blue Crab Advisory Committee, 2000-2002. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Bi-State Blue Crab Advisory Committee, 2002-2003. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Chesapeake Bay Agreement 2000, 2002-2003. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Chesapeake Bay Agreement 2000--Local Government Advisory Committee, 1998-2002. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Chesapeake Bay Agreement 2000--Priorities for Secretary of Natural Resources, 2002. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Chesapeake Bay Agreement 2000--Revised Agreement, 2000. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Chesapeake Bay Agreement 2000--Signing Ceremony, 2000. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Chesapeake Bay Agreement 2000--Signing Ceremony, 2000. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Chesapeake Bay Agreement 2000--Signing Ceremony, 2000. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Chesapeake Bay Agreement 2000--Toxics Strategy, 1994. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Chesapeake Bay Blue Ribbon Finance Panel, 2004. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Chesapeake Bay Blue Ribbon Finance Panel, 2004. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Chesapeake Bay Blue Ribbon Finance Panel, 2004. (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2002. (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2002. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2002. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2002. (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2002. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2002. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2003. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2003. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2003. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2003. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2003. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2003. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2003. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2004. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2005. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2005. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2005. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2005. (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2005. (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2005. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2005. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2005. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Chesapeake Executive Council, 2005. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Citizens Advisory Committee to the Chesapeake Executive Council, 2001-2004. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Joint Meeting of Senate Agriculture, Conservation and Natural Resources and House Agriculture, Chesapeake, and Natural Resources Committees, 2004. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Joint Meeting of Senate Agriculture, Conservation and Natural Resources and House Agriculture, Chesapeake, and Natural Resources Committees, 2004. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Joint Meeting of Senate Agriculture, Conservation and Natural Resources and House Agriculture, Chesapeake, and Natural Resources Committees, 2004. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2002. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2003. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2003. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2003. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2003. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2003. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2003. (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2004. (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2004. (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2004. (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2004. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2004. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2004. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2004. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2004. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2004. (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2004. (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2004. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2005. (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2005. (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2005. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2005. (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Principals' Staff Committee, 2005. (Box 10, Folder 13)